forward through eight. We put on the consent agenda and there are no questions on any of those
items that are entertaining a motion to approve.
I just got one question on seven. I guess I'm going to pull that out.
So we're going to pull item seven out and we'll consider item four five six and eight. If there
are no questions on those, do we have a motion to approve?
Those two. In a second. Second. O call please.
All right. For a second. All right.
I'm Sarah and there's approved termination contract later for contract number C13-11 with
cutting-edge long services. 90 day notice.
Salicious and you speak to that issue.
This is just the final step once we brought all the moving back in-house. This was the
one contract that we still had out that we wanted to make sure it was taken care of
after you brought it in-house. And the term. The term in that contract was originally what?
This term we wanted to fix it for you. The June and July one.
And so this is actually term in a long July one.
No, it will terminate 90 days from.
So a couple of weeks. A couple of weeks. A couple of weeks.
Yeah. A couple of weeks.
But also gives them notice that we're not going to do that. Right.
Yes. So we'll be ready to take over.
Yes, sir. Yes. But that's all.
We're interviewing people right now.
Okay. So we're interviewing people right now.
And the other contract, the bad gentleman had pulled out already anyway.
Right. So he was the one that did not want to anyone to do it.
So we need a motion to approve item seven.
Motion. Second.
Roll call breaks.
Something.
That's just to item nine.
Which is order to many.
Section 24153.
Article 3.
Authorize the city manager to allow an exception.
That deals specifically with servers and servers disposal.
And Christie, how are you? Good.
Good.
So recently we've been with ran across a couple of situations where it is necessary for us to allow
a connection to our sewer of a meter of water or killing water or something of that nature that
needs to go to the sewer plant and be treated.
Our ordinance, the way that it's currently written, just prohibits it and doesn't allow for
any connections like that to happen.
Several other ordinances with other cities have exactly the same wording as ours.
But with that little extra line in there that says unless permitted by the city manager.
So we've gone back and.
basically just added that sentence to the current ordinance that we have in there that on a case-by-case basis
These would go before Dean and he would review him and make a decision on whether it was a
Good benefit to allow that connection. So is this summer? It's not buying water from us ready. They need to sue
I exactly we can give you the two examples right now. It's first off. It's the root 66 land in the O'Robinson building that they're converting
They need a place to be able to have the condensation from their conditioners drain out
In order to if they were to follow other code, they would have to
They've explained it to me. It'd be almost a $30,000 change and they're a project to be able to
Revert it out into the alleyway
Again, this is just condensation from an air conditioner
So you're talking just a few gallons a day literally going into the sewer. The second one is going to be for the splash pad
Once the
Once the eco-hitcher building is demolished and ODQ is completed
There'll be a very small vault on the property that will have the sun pump that's already there that we use for the groundwater to keep the
Cloraming plume from expanding
That some pump needs to go into a sanitary sewer not a storm sewer and again is just a very little amount of water per day that would be going in
So these are the types of cases. It's not like there'd be a wholesale amount of water and in fact
EPA and groups like that really keep an eye on us to make sure that we're not putting storm water or large amounts of water into the storm system to overcharge our
Storm sewer plant
But these are very small items and just to make sure that we're following code. We're asking for this change
so
I'm just curious
Will this see on that vault?
And I mean is it are we really we are the ones that will be the part of the agreement was after the vault is in place and all that
We would be maintaining the sun pump and the operation of the sun pump
I'm not saying it didn't need to go through sewer, but it's not a water
And again the the sun pump is the groundwater that will be pumped in
I got one quote on this comment say line, you know with that
Building in that structure there and then wanting to do this
What are we currently monitoring all the other facilities down there? There's nobody else doing this or we don't
Everybody to want to come in fact the thing is is that the building nobody's doing that when they took it over
When it was the church and all that predictors a lot and they they're probably a lot of them. So it's almost a case by case basis that
We probably have a lot of connections that would not need it, but if somebody's
Renovating a building or something we'd be making those calls that as the others are grandfathers
You
Yeah, it was if it was done before 1964. I'm part of the challenge.
It's no one on any AC. You're no example. Right. That's part of the challenge.
I know of the new facilities. Yeah.
I've been warned that they can't do that. So I just want to make sure if it's a case by case.
I want them to be able to come and do that.
Absolutely. Yes. Different than in the past, we were approached by this.
And so the challenge was on us to try to figure out a way to help.
To help make this happen. And other communities do it.
And I really get a course of business. We just help not.
And this allows us to apply some common sense.
Well, I would say that other communities have this same ordinance written the way that we're asking to change to the ordinance.
So now we have a social business, but I have the opportunity to do it when it's necessary.
Exactly.
Any other questions? Okay.
We have motion to approve.
Item 9.
Motion to approve.
Sir.
Go, Paul.
Johnson.
All right.
Sure.
I have to remind you, I was an approving community financial support and fee waiver to the Oklahoma Affordable Housing Partners LLC.
For a donation of structures located at 227.
And after the east and 524.
And for the east and construction and single family dwelling at the same location.
And as far as the root 66 landing overall project.
This is the outline possible.
Yes. This is the last piece of property.
We had another piece of property that they were going to develop on.
And that is vacant right now.
But there were some challenges that we were running into with the sewer line.
And so this was actually this is a property that was is right next door to another property that I came to you guys on.
I came months ago to wave the fees to dimmer it and we building a house next to it.
So when the other property fell through, they worked really hard to contact the owner of this property.
It was already on the dimmer list.
And we did to come down and it's just a good thing because we'll have two new houses right there.
Next to each other instead of a new house and not so good house.
There's actually three structures on this property.
That's the main house and if you go to the other page timer.
This is the structure that's behind it.
So it's one lot.
There's actually two houses on it.
And pictures of the inside of these homes were in my presentation.
I did on code components a few weeks ago.
So.
There's actually two addresses listed here.
It's it's one legal description.
Lot nine block 64 of original platform that there are there are two structures that had separate utilities.
And that's why you have two addresses.
So they have no authorization or third nor the extra basically the same.
the same law. One just faces third street, the other faces
F. Right. So what I'm playing that whole lot. The whole lot. And then I'm going to
build a new house. Right. Awesome. Good. So these were currently own. One of them was
currently own. The whole property was currently owned by a lady here in town
that was not obviously. She has not taken care of them. Yeah. And it's 66
actually owns it now. They purchased it from the citizen that
I'm doing. And so they have ownership of it. And we're going to take it.
But we should add a free 66 had not done that. We would have torn it down. Yeah.
It was coming down in this next round anyway. And that it was just a good opportunity
to go ahead and get a utility customer on it now. Instead of being responsible for
it. And the fee waiver. These are the same fees that we've waived on the other
properties. Exactly the same thing that we did on 225. It'll be waiving the fees
for the demolition, which is a little over $8,000 to have it to have the
properties. All the structures on the demo and taking care of. All the structures.
Yes. There's a storage shed and then the two homes that were on that piece of
property. And then it's waiving the same permits and inspection fees that we've
waived on the other work involved in the project from its 66. It doesn't waive the
inspections but it waives those fees.
Of course, you had to notice if those had foundations as opposed to pure and
that if they had foundations or foundations or be gone. Everything.
It's a requirement on any property that the city demos. That it's taken down to like
18 inches below. The grade to make sure that they remove all the
fittings and everything on the property and then bring back in dirt to make it
supposed to make it back to a moving condition.
You drive by the side. There's a vacant lot directly to the south and that's a house
that we've already removed and you'll see that just as Christy said, it's
to mowing condition. These will be taken down to the same standard and then we'll
start building two new homes there.
I don't want to be there too far off but on with the structures that are being put
back in currently in other areas but on this one I've already installing sidewalks
on the front of these structures.
So we actually, our sidewalks in our community are kind of hidden
lists and some are in good shape and some aren't in good shape.
Travis and I actually just talked to them last week and we're coming to us with
the plan of where they plan to replace sidewalk and where they
wouldn't replace sidewalk based on the area around it where it wouldn't make
sense for a house to happen.
I'll just go to some of these old ones. There is sidewalks there including that's going to get
I think two of great to be able to be what we're trying to do is if the neighborhood has a sidewalk, they'll put in a sidewalk
They'll attach if there are no sidewalks in that neighborhood then they won't put in a sidewalk because it'll just be a sidewalk to nowhere
And we're saying day
60-60
You need any other questions
Tell them we're not opposed to starting a new fan if they were right
I had a sign
I'm tired
No other questions
Thank you Mike
Most of our program
Second
Go call please
Joseph
Fourth or
Fourth
I don't know what I'm in discussion with the special city council meeting on Tuesday March 28th, 2015
I'm going to put this on and just to make sure we talk about what we're trying to accomplish
Just to prove the benefited in by this watching tonight
We have a charter elections scheduled for April 4th
Hopefully this is not the first time you hear it because I know the news record is ran the full charter on three different occasions
There's been a letter to the editor, summarizing some of the changes that we're asking the citizens to approve
Basically we're updating the charter
Modernizing with a guest to be another appropriate term
And we're going to make sure that all of my half questions has an opportunity to ask questions
Even though we've discussed it all of a dozen council meetings
And it's been on the post to the genders
We just want to make sure that any citizens at my half a question
Have one last chance to ask those questions before the vote
And so this will be actually a week before the vote next March 28th
That's what is normally our council work session
And it usually starts at 4 o'clock in the afternoon
We just do it maybe larger issue that takes a lot of discussion and time
Because we want to be sensitive to people's work schedules
We're going to this will technically be a special meeting because we're changing the time to 530
To give as many people that want to an opportunity to attend
So that will be next Tuesday March 28th
Here at the Civic Center in the back of the banquet room at 530
And I think that the only thing on the agenda is that we're planning right now is then we'll be the only thing
That's the same. Well some urgent issue comes up certainly we would add that and do it
But it's our plan to be available
The council will be available staff will be available
Topies of the proposed charter will be available
And while I'm on that topic
If anybody is watching you and wants to do some homework in advance
You can go to the city website
There's a link to the charter or you can just stop my city hall to you till the office
be provided a copy. So, again, the elections they're
professed, and we want to do everything we can to communicate with
any and all citizens that have any questions or concerns about what
we're trying to accomplish. And what you're getting is basically just a
modernization of our charter to bring it into the 21st century since it was
written in 1910. It still has a lot of language from 1910 and that.
We're going to do more details than that tonight, but we're encouraging
you when it's watching to please make an effort to be here if you have any
questions or concerns. Do you need anything to add or any council members any
questions? I hope I know we've just kind of springed that on you, but it'll be
five thirty next Tuesday. I hope everybody can be here.
Item 12 is new business. Do you need new business under this agenda?
No, sir. Okay. Item 13 is staff reports are in your packet.
Item 14 is mayor and council announcements and the announcements any one?
Okay. Absolutely. We're just going to do his thing.
See the major communications team. Two items a lot of to go. One is as we stand right
now, we've collected 182 tons as part of our spring.
I'm going to record and we're all around half still.
Yeah. I think we close.
I believe we're averaging about 30 to 32 tons a day.
Yes, the way it's coming out. So if you have seen the neighborhoods where we're
about to collect, there are a lot of things on the curb. So a lot of people are paying
attention to it. Second item I'd like to talk about, I hope I'm kind of comes back
into this in a moment because he was involved with this as well. You might have
seen an article in the paper recently that blended it a very good article about my appearance
before the inner tribal council. And I want to just give a report that with this help and
Senator Borgstrom's help, we've been in touch with the with our dot about some improvements
along Stephen and his board of art to deal with the flooding. Also state highway 125 and also
the intersection that the inner tribal council got started about the turn pipe.
A few things to try to make this process going and I want to thank Tyler for this is that after
a meeting there was just some frustration, I think there was even the headline which is probably
appropriate about really how long the project is taking and if there were some short term
things that could potentially be done at that intersection of the turn pipe. And one of the
things that Chief Spartan for example said is just right now, is there anything we can do
about the signalization that exists right now to try to help with some of the turns, so let's
some of the turn movements. Right now Oda is saying that if all of the stars align, we might be able
to see a reconstruction they're on about two years or so. But we'll just see how that goes
but they're trying to move it along quickly. So talking about with our crews that work on
signalization we had a few options that they came up with and we have given that to the director
about odd and we hope that they'll start looking at that and seeing maybe we can do that as a joint
project. It'd be basically something that could last for two years. Might be able to provide some
protected turns things such as that. In fact, I don't know if you want to join in and explain
some of the things we might be looking at. We'll talk about split phasing. I'm sorry for
getting off the turn back if we're coming on 69 a you know how they they turn the same time
what we could look at making those change at different times. But within south yes they would change
at different times so that would be split phasing and we would add a signal to those heads so you
could turn and we've also looked at updating the loops or putting cameras up there to send
traffic better. If you notice if you come off the turn pack if people don't pull up to that white line
the traffic will start to back up because they're not picking up on that loop right there so we
talked about maybe putting some more sensors farther back to you touch that. That's how. And one of the
things that we're really talking about too is that we work with our dogs who do this in a couple of
just a couple of years. I want to make sure that for example the cameras if we were to
install the cameras and then when they do the complete rebuild which we probably have more signalization
and cameras that would be specific to that rebuild if we had those as surplus could we put those
in other locations like for example we're talking about 22nd and May right by Brahms. I think that
some cameras there will probably help to turn signals quite a bit more than the you know in
eightement loops so we're just trying to think ahead on that but I just want to hear it be a wherever
we're working on. The second project that we really discussed strongly with our dog is that they
everybody's aware that they're planning on re-decking the state holiday 125 bridge starting in 2018 and that
means that bridge is going to be closed when they do through the decking and it's just seen to us that
we just be the opportune time if they're going to be doing that document to do some type of an improvement
on the approaches to the bridge to raise them up maybe not completely out of the 100 year flood event
but raise them up enough that they're not getting flooded all the time. In my short time here I think we've
had to close at at least three times just because of spring rains or even December rains. They're
open to that they mean no doubt staff but they have a lot of processes that they have to go through
and one of the first processes they have to go through is doing a feasibility study and just the way the
state works to get somebody on board to do a feasibility study would take quite a bit of time.
and we're talking about this project starting next year.
So I suggested that since we have also an associate's on board,
that if they would accept the feasibility study,
that we would go ahead and move on the feasibility study
and get it taken care of,
because there would be no time better to do that
than when that bridge is closed.
I mean, it just makes absolute sense.
So I believe in your next agenda,
Alicia's working on the request proposal
with us and you'll have an agenda item there.
And we hope that, you know, they'll accept it,
because there will have the engineer stamp
from all of a sudden that they can accept that.
There's some other environmental requirements
that they would have to meet.
But we hope that we can maybe move that project up too,
because in all reality, that would be a fairly engineering wise.
It'd be a very simple project to putting in some culverts
and just basically raising the elevation of the road.
So that's something that's going to be coming your way too.
I want you to be aware of.
So that's my report.
We don't know if there's anything you'd want to add on that.
No, I would say it was encouraging, I said in on that meeting.
And it was encouraging, personally, the plan is a plan.
Then you have to fund it.
So that's why I appreciate being coming up with the idea that, hey,
we'll let us look at the feasibility study
and the cost, and maybe we can provide that part of it.
And keep moving in a pace that fits the schedule that they're already on.
You know, there are, obviously, our idea of goal is to raise 125
and Steve Owens.
But just getting one or the other would make a big difference
for our community when it does flood.
As far as ingress an egress and emergency services to that part of town.
Yeah, Steve Owens, of course, would be a much, much larger project.
And they're going to take a look at that also.
But that will be a longer term project if we can, if we can push it through.
So that's all.
So we're going to add item 16, which is a journey.
And I'll make that motion.
Do we have a second?
I'll start.
Roll call, please.
So, I start this.
All right.